AROMATIC COMPOUNDS
 Aromaticity, the property of being aromatic is possessed by compounds having specific electronic structure characterised by Hückel (4n+2)π electron rule.
 The nature of groups or substituents attached to benzene ring is responsible for activation or deactivation of the benzene ring towards further electrophilic substitution and also for orientation of the incoming group. Some of 
the polynuclear hydrocarbons having fused benzene ring system have carcinogenic property.
