CHEMICAL BONDING AND MOLECULAR STRUCTURE

Kössel’s first insight into the mechanism of formation of electropositive and electronegative ions related the process to the attainment of noble gas configurations by the respective ions. Electrostatic attraction between ions is
 the cause for their stability. This gives the concept of electrovalency. The first description of covalent bonding was provided by Lewis in terms of the sharing of electron pairs between atoms and he related the process to the 
attainment of noble gas configurations by reacting atoms as a result of sharing of electrons. The Lewis dot symbols show the number of valence electrons of the atoms of a given element and Lewis dot structures show pictorial 
representations of bonding in molecules. An ionic compound is pictured as a three-dimensional aggregation of positive and negative ions in an ordered arrangement called the crystal lattice. In a crystalline solid there is a 
charge balance between the positive and negative ions. The crystal lattice is stabilized by the enthalpy of lattice formation. While a single covalent bond is formed by sharing of an electron pair between two atoms, multiple 
bonds result from the sharing of two or three electron pairs. Some bonded atoms have additional pairs of electrons not involved in bonding. These are called lonepairs of electrons. A Lewis dot structure shows the arrangement 
of bonded pairs and lone pairs around each atom in a molecule.


