THE LAWS
Boyle’s law states that under isothermal condition, pressure of a fixed amount of a gas is inversely proportional to its volume. Charles’ law is a 
 relationship between volume and absolute temperature under isobaric condition. It states that volume of a fixed amount of gas is directly proportional to its absolute temperature V T ∝ ( ). If state of a gas is represented by p1, V1
 and T1 and it changes to state at p2, V2 and T2, then relationship between these two states is given by combined as law according to which p V Tp VT1 112 22 = . Any one of the variables of this gas can be found out if other five
 variables are known. Avogadro law states that equal volumes of all gases under same conditions of temperature and pressure contain equal number of molecules. Dalton’s law of partial pressure states that total pressure exerted
 by a mixture of non-reacting gases is equal to the sum of partial pressures exerted by them. Thus p = p1+p2+p3+ ... . Relationship between pressure, volume, temperature and number of moles of a gas describes its state and is
 called equation of state of the gas.