THERMOCHEMISTRY
Enthalpy change, ∆H = ∆U + ∆ngRT, can be found directly from the heat changes at constant pressure, ∆H = qp. There are varieties of enthalpy changes. Changes of phase such as 
melting, vaporization and sublimation usually occur at constant temperature and can be characterized by enthalpy changes which are always positive. Enthalpy of formation, combustion and other enthalpy changes can be 
 calculated using Hess’s law. Enthalpy change for chemical reactions can be determined by ∆ ∆ ∆ r i f i f if H a H b H = ( )− ( ) ∑∑ products reactions and in gaseous state by ∆rH0 = Σ bond enthalpies of the reactants – Σ bond
 enthalpies of the products First law of thermodynamics does not guide us about the direction of chemical reactions i.e., what is the driving force of a chemical reaction. For isolated systems, ∆U = 0. We define another state 
function, S, entropy for this purpose. Entropy is a measure of disorder or randomness. For a spontaneous change, total entropy change is positive. Therefore, for an isolated system, ∆U = 0, ∆S > 0, so entropy change 
distinguishes a spontaneous change, while energy change does not. Entropy changes can be measured by the equation ∆S =qrev T for a reversible process.qrev T is independent of path.Chemical reactions are generally carried
 at constant pressure, so we define another state function Gibbs energy, G, which is related to entropy and enthalpy changes of the system by the equation: ∆rG = ∆rH – T ∆rS For a spontaneous change, ∆Gsys < 0 and at 
equilibrium, ∆Gsys = 0. Standard Gibbs energy change is related to equilibrium constant by ∆rG0 = – RT ln K. K can be calculated from this equation, if we know ∆rG0 which can be found from . Temperature is an important
 factor in the equation. Many reactions which are non-spontaneous at low temperature, are made spontaneous at high temperature for systems having positive entropy of reaction.
