THE THERMODYNAMIC VARIABLES
∆U,  change in internal energy, depends on initial and final states only and is a state function, whereas q and w depend on the path and are not the state functions. We follow sign conventions of q and w by giving the positive 
sign to these quantities when these are added to the system. We can measure the transfer of heat from one system to another which causes the change in temperature. The magnitude of rise in temperature depends on the
 heat capacity (C) of a substance. Therefore, heat absorbed or evolved is q =  C∆T. Work can be measured by w = –pex∆V, in case of expansion of gases. Under reversible process, we can put pex = p for infinitesimal changes in the 
volume making wrev = – p dV. In this condition, we can use gas equation, pV = nRT. At constant volume, w = 0, then ∆U = qV , heat transfer at constant volume. But in study of chemical reactions, we usually have constant pressure
. We define another state function enthalpy. 
