THERMODYNAMICS-INTRODUCTION

Thermodynamics deals with energy changes in chemical or physical processes and enables us to study these
 changes quantitatively and to make useful predictions. For these purposes, we divide the universe into the 
system andthe surroundings. Chemical or physical processes lead to evolution or absorption of heat (q), part of
 which may be converted into work (w). These quantities are related through the first law of thermodynamics
 via ∆U = q + w. 

